<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="//assets/xslt/atom.xslt" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="//assets/css/atom.css" ?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<id>https://sgrse.de//</id>
	<title>sgrse</title>
	<updated>2024-10-11T11:39:01+00:00</updated>

	<subtitle>This describes my website on the footer</subtitle>

	
		
		<author>
			
				<name>Sebastian Günther</name>
			
			
			
		</author>
	

	<link href="https://sgrse.de//atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link href="https://sgrse.de//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />

	<generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator>

	
		<entry>
			<id>https://sgrse.de//projects/wind-park/</id>
			<title>Wind Farm</title>
			<link href="https://sgrse.de//projects/wind-park/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wind Farm" />
			<updated>2024-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>Sebastian Günther</name>
					
					
						<email>info@sgrse.de</email>
					
					
						<uri>https://sgrse.de/</uri>
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>An energy storage dimensioning tool for wind farm operators to assess the viability of incorporating storage systems. It analyzes power profiles and optimizes storage parameters such as technology, size, and operational strategy. It empowers operators to make informed, profitable decisions with the option to commercialize the tool as a service for other wind farm operators.</summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="https://sgrse.de//projects/wind-park/">&lt;p&gt;The tool was designed to help wind farm
operators determine the feasibility of integrating energy storage systems into
their wind farms. Wind farms often face curtailment, where excess energy
generated by wind turbines cannot be utilized or stored, leading to revenue
losses. This tool addresses the need to optimize energy storage integration,
allowing operators to store curtailed energy and sell it later when prices are
more favorable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project involved developing a comprehensive mathematical model that analyzed
power profiles from wind farms, considering technical constraints such as
storage capacity, efficiency, and cost-effectiveness. The model explored various
storage technologies, including their charging and discharging characteristics,
response times, and costs. The tool provides a set of optimal storage
configurations based on the unique needs of each wind farm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to assessing the technical feasibility, the tool includes an
economic evaluation, helping operators determine whether investing in energy
storage would be profitable. By analyzing both CAPEX and OPEX, as well as
potential revenue from energy sales, it ensures that all financial aspects are
considered. The result is not just a simple yes or no but an in-depth analysis
of the ideal storage technology, size, and operational strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most valuable features of this tool is its scalability. Wind farm
operators can apply it across multiple sites, automatically adjusting to
different wind farm configurations and power profiles. This scalability enhances
the tool’s applicability across a wide range of scenarios, making it a valuable
asset for operators managing multiple wind farms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the tool can be commercialized as a service. Operators can offer the
dimensioning service to other wind farm owners, creating an additional revenue
stream while optimizing their own energy storage systems. This dual function of
the tool increases its overall value and market potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the tool’s advanced integration capabilities ensure smooth data
exchange with existing systems. Developed with Python and incorporating linear
programming and optimization algorithms, the tool is computationally efficient
and capable of handling large datasets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;button-container&quot;&gt;


&lt;a class=&quot;left button tiny radius&quot; href=&quot;https://sgrse.de//projects/green-residential-area/&quot;&gt;Green Residential Area&lt;span class=&quot;icon-chevron-right&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;a class=&quot;right button tiny radius&quot; href=&quot;https://sgrse.de//projects/&quot;&gt;Project Overview&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>

			
				<category term="projects" />
			
			

			<published>2024-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<id>https://sgrse.de//projects/green-residential-area/</id>
			<title>Green Residential Area</title>
			<link href="https://sgrse.de//projects/green-residential-area/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Green Residential Area" />
			<updated>2024-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>Sebastian Günther</name>
					
					
						<email>info@sgrse.de</email>
					
					
						<uri>https://sgrse.de/</uri>
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>This project designed an optimized energy system for a sustainable residential community. By simulating energy demand for heating, cooling, and electricity, it analyzed the integration of PV systems, storage, and demand-side management. The goal was to increase self-consumption rates and minimize grid reliance through smart energy planning and renewable technologies.</summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="https://sgrse.de//projects/green-residential-area/">&lt;p&gt;This project aimed to develop an optimized
energy model for a sustainable residential community. The project explored
various scenarios to balance energy efficiency with renewable energy
integration, focusing on heating, cooling, and electricity demands. It analyzed
how different building types, insulation standards, and renewable energy sources
like photovoltaic (PV) systems could impact energy use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Detailed consumption profiles for electricity, heating, and hot water were
generated through simulations, creating time-resolved power consumption and
generation profiles for a thorough analysis of the community’s energy needs. 
Beyond matching energy use with production, the project investigated how energy
storage and demand-side management could maximize self-consumption and reduce
grid dependence. Adjusting energy use, such as shifting tasks to periods of high
PV generation, helped align demand with production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Energy storage for electricity and heat, along with combined heat and power
(CHP) units, were also explored to further reduce energy imports and ensure a
stable power supply for the community. 
The simulations provided valuable insights into varying input parameters,
helping to design a flexible system that can adapt to weather fluctuations or
different energy demands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the project demonstrates how smart
energy planning, renewable energy, and storage solutions can create efficient,
self-sustaining residential areas that contribute significantly to the energy
transition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;button-container&quot;&gt;

&lt;a class=&quot;left button tiny radius icon-chevron-left r15&quot; href=&quot;https://sgrse.de//projects/wind-park/&quot;&gt;Wind Farm&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;a class=&quot;left button tiny radius&quot; href=&quot;https://sgrse.de//projects/flywheel/&quot;&gt;Flywheel&lt;span class=&quot;icon-chevron-right&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;a class=&quot;right button tiny radius&quot; href=&quot;https://sgrse.de//projects/&quot;&gt;Project Overview&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>

			
				<category term="projects" />
			
			

			<published>2024-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<id>https://sgrse.de//projects/flywheel/</id>
			<title>Flywheel</title>
			<link href="https://sgrse.de//projects/flywheel/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flywheel" />
			<updated>2024-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>Sebastian Günther</name>
					
					
						<email>info@sgrse.de</email>
					
					
						<uri>https://sgrse.de/</uri>
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>A 200 Wh flywheel energy storage system for academic research and demonstration. Featuring a high-strengh aluminum and CFRP rotor, it operates at 25,000 rpm, powered by a 3.5 kW synchronous motor. The prototype enables the study of key flywheel phenomena like thermal behavior and rotordynamics, making it a valuable tool for both research and education.</summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="https://sgrse.de//projects/flywheel/">&lt;p&gt;Flywheel energy storage systems
(FESS) stand out as a promising technology due to their high cycle life, rapid
response time, and efficient power-to-energy ratio. This project aimed to design
and construct a laboratory-scale flywheel system to serve both as a research
demonstrator and as an educational tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resulting prototype is a 200 Wh flywheel energy storage system, featuring a
rotor composed of high-strength aluminum and carbon fiber reinforced plastic
(CFRP). It spins at a nominal speed of 25,000 rpm, powered by a 3.5 kW permanent
magnet synchronous motor (PMSM). The flywheel operates at overcritical speeds
with medium vacuum conditions, minimizing windage losses and ensuring optimal
performance. Key components, such as the spindle bearings and power electronics,
were carefully selected to ensure smooth operation and control, even under
isolated conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the primary goals of this project was to design a system capable of
demonstrating the key features of flywheel technology. The FESS was built to
showcase flywheel capabilities at exhibitions and in academic settings, with
enough power to brew up to five cups of coffee on a single charge. This vivid
demonstration helps make the technology tangible, attracting interest in both
research and industry. Additionally, the system serves as a laboratory tool for
students, allowing them to study flywheel-specific phenomena such as dynamic
behavior, thermal response, and energy losses in real-time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A significant aspect of the design was the consideration of thermodynamic
behavior and rotordynamics. A lumped parameter model was developed to estimate
temperature distribution, and the system’s rotordynamics were tuned using finite
element methods (FEM). This ensured that the flywheel operates safely and
efficiently, even at high speeds. The FESS’s modular setup also facilitates
research into various system parameters, such as vacuum levels, windage losses,
and bearing performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The construction of the flywheel system involved a comprehensive 3D model and
technical drawings, ensuring precision and safety in every component. The design
was iterative, allowing for adjustments based on testing and simulations.
Mechanical safety considerations, such as stress distribution and tolerance for
overspeed, were integrated into the design to minimize the risk of failure. The
system’s housing and auxiliary equipment provide robust protection, while
maintaining a relatively compact form factor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;button-container&quot;&gt;

&lt;a class=&quot;left button tiny radius icon-chevron-left r15&quot; href=&quot;https://sgrse.de//projects/green-residential-area/&quot;&gt;Green Residential Area&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;a class=&quot;left button tiny radius&quot; href=&quot;https://sgrse.de//projects/tram-system/&quot;&gt;Tram System&lt;span class=&quot;icon-chevron-right&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;a class=&quot;right button tiny radius&quot; href=&quot;https://sgrse.de//projects/&quot;&gt;Project Overview&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>

			
				<category term="projects" />
			
			

			<published>2024-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<id>https://sgrse.de//projects/tram-system/</id>
			<title>Tram System</title>
			<link href="https://sgrse.de//projects/tram-system/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tram System" />
			<updated>2024-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>Sebastian Günther</name>
					
					
						<email>info@sgrse.de</email>
					
					
						<uri>https://sgrse.de/</uri>
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>A simulation framework to optimize tram network energy use, incorporating energy storage. The program allows scalable modeling, detailed energy calculations, timetable creation, and integration with MATLAB/Simulink libraries. External data management, optimization algorithms, and flexible storage placement make this a robust tool for energy savings in tram systems.</summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="https://sgrse.de//projects/tram-system/">&lt;p&gt;The project involves the development and optimization of a MATLAB/Simulink/SimPowerSystems
program to simulate electrical tram networks, which is adaptable to other
networks such as factories that either operate with either AC or DC power. The system
is designed with modularity in mind, allowing for easy scalability, detailed
calculation of route energy requirements (accounting for height and curve
profiles), and flexible integration of Simulink libraries and block-based
construction for adjustments and improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key features include the ability to optimize the placement and sizing of
flywheel energy storage systems, which enhance energy savings by storing and
discharging energy at appropriate times. The simulation is highly customizable,
offering adjustable simulation accuracy, external model generation via XML, and
effective post-processing of simulation data. The simulation allows for precise
timetable and load cycle creation in a tabular format and considers the
influence of energy sources, including substation positioning and the direction
of tram movement on either track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project utilizes MATLAB functions to generate train schedules, manage
simulation data, and control the flow of information between SimPowerSystems and
external modules. It also automates the block and model generation in
Simulink/SimPowerSystems based on track and network data provided via XML,
ensuring seamless integration of electrical and mechanical models. This
high-level markup file approach simplifies the customization of complex track
systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The placement and sizing of energy storage systems along the tram network are
optimized using external genetic and evolutionary algorithms, which interface
with MATLAB through XML. This design allows for flexible modifications and
enhancements, making the program a powerful tool for energy management in tram
systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;button-container&quot;&gt;

&lt;a class=&quot;left button tiny radius icon-chevron-left r15&quot; href=&quot;https://sgrse.de//projects/flywheel/&quot;&gt;Flywheel&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;a class=&quot;left button tiny radius&quot; href=&quot;https://sgrse.de//projects/rotary-table/&quot;&gt;Rotary Table&lt;span class=&quot;icon-chevron-right&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;a class=&quot;right button tiny radius&quot; href=&quot;https://sgrse.de//projects/&quot;&gt;Project Overview&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>

			
				<category term="projects" />
			
			

			<published>2024-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<id>https://sgrse.de//projects/rotary-table/</id>
			<title>Rotary Table</title>
			<link href="https://sgrse.de//projects/rotary-table/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rotary Table" />
			<updated>2024-09-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>Sebastian Günther</name>
					
					
						<email>info@sgrse.de</email>
					
					
						<uri>https://sgrse.de/</uri>
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>This project developed a numerically controlled rotary table integrated with a Laser Scanning Vibrometer for structural health monitoring. It automates the precise measurement of wave propagation in curved composite structures, such as carbon fiber reinforced polymers (CFRP). The system enables accurate and efficient data collection through automated measurement cycles.</summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="https://sgrse.de//projects/rotary-table/">&lt;p&gt;This project realized a custom-built numerically controlled (NC) rotary table, designed
specifically for research into curved composite structures using a Laser
Scanning Vibrometer (LSV). The system allows automated, high-precision
measurement of wave propagation in cylindrical components like carbon fiber
reinforced polymer (CFRP) structures, which are common in aerospace and other
safety-critical applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rotary table automates the rotation of test objects in small, predefined
angles, making it possible to perform detailed measurements across the entire
surface without the need to manually adjust the experimental setup. This
functionality is critical for capturing accurate data in structural health
monitoring (SHM), where detecting internal damage, such as delamination, can
prevent catastrophic failure in operational environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this project, I designed and implemented the mechanical system, including the
shaft, bearings, and gear components. Electrical integration involved selecting
and programming a stepper motor control system that interfaces seamlessly with
the Polytec Laser Scanning Vibrometer software, automating the measurement cycle
for efficient data collection. The system is fully capable of performing
automated cycles of rotation and measurement, significantly enhancing the
precision of wave propagation studies in curved structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond its mechanical and electrical components, the rotary table was developed
with extensibility in mind. The design allows for additional axes or sensors to
be easily added, making it suitable for a wide range of SHM studies. For
example, the addition of an XY table on top of the rotary table can extend its
capabilities further. The low-cost design makes it a valuable asset for research
laboratories that need high precision without the expense of commercial systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although designed primarily for laboratory use, the rotary table provides
significant flexibility in terms of future applications. Its modular
construction and slip ring allow for extensive modifications, and it supports
integration with various data acquisition systems, offering the potential for
future upgrades or more complex experimental setups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project successfully met its objectives, delivering an
affordable, functional rotary table for structural health monitoring research.
The system’s ability to handle automated measurement cycles offers a scalable
solution that bridges the gap between manual measurements and high-end
commercial systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;button-container&quot;&gt;

&lt;a class=&quot;left button tiny radius icon-chevron-left r15&quot; href=&quot;https://sgrse.de//projects/tram-system/&quot;&gt;Tram System&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;a class=&quot;left button tiny radius&quot; href=&quot;https://sgrse.de//projects/others/&quot;&gt;Further Service Examples&lt;span class=&quot;icon-chevron-right&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;a class=&quot;right button tiny radius&quot; href=&quot;https://sgrse.de//projects/&quot;&gt;Project Overview&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>

			
				<category term="projects" />
			
			

			<published>2024-09-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<id>https://sgrse.de//projects/others/</id>
			<title>Further Service Examples</title>
			<link href="https://sgrse.de//projects/others/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Further Service Examples" />
			<updated>2024-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>Sebastian Günther</name>
					
					
						<email>info@sgrse.de</email>
					
					
						<uri>https://sgrse.de/</uri>
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>Still wondering what I can offer? Here&apos;s a range of high-level and specialized examples of the projects you can trust me with. Whether it&apos;s scaling computations on high-performance clusters, accelerating existing models, consulting on software architecture, or bridging knowledge transfer between research institutes and industry—you’re in capable hands with me.</summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="https://sgrse.de//projects/others/">&lt;h4 id=&quot;core-services&quot;&gt;Core Services&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scaling calculations on high-performance computers (HPC).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accelerating existing models through refactoring with more efficient
algorithms or programming languages.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Optimizing energy management in smart grids with machine learning
algorithms.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developing load forecasting algorithms for microgrids&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Development of a supervisory agent controlling an autonomous fleet in
warehouses using model-predictive control.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Implementing machine learning algorithms for pattern recognition in large
datasets to detect anomalies in production processes early.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating digital twins for monitoring and optimizing production systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;related-activities&quot;&gt;Related Activities&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supporting project teams at the intersection of research and software
development.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transitioning a prototype project into a university-supported research
project and developing a research funding proposal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Facilitating knowledge transfer between research institutes and industry
partners.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conducting feasibility studies for new technological approaches.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Providing lectures and training.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consulting and advising on improving the software architecture of existing
systems.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advising on integrating artificial intelligence into existing production
processes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating white papers and studies on new technological developments and
their applications.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Strategic consulting for planning and implementing digital transformation
projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;prototyping-for-mechatronic-systems&quot;&gt;Prototyping for Mechatronic Systems&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prototyping automated test stands for quality assurance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Designing intelligent sensor-actuator systems.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developing integrated sensor modules for machine and plant monitoring.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building robotic assistance systems for manual manufacturing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developing adaptive damping systems to reduce vibrations in components.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating smart components with piezoceramics and adaptive systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;excluded-services&quot;&gt;Excluded Services&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Standard tasks such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Designing photovoltaic systems for residential buildings.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Designing PID controllers for standardized process chains.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GUI development for an existing CLI-based calculation tool.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developing simple database applications without analytical components.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dimensioning standard air conditioning systems for office buildings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although these tasks can be handled, there are specialized professionals who can
perform them faster, cheaper, and better. Instead, I focus on challenges that
require non-standardized modeling and unique solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;button-container&quot;&gt;

&lt;a class=&quot;left button tiny radius icon-chevron-left r15&quot; href=&quot;https://sgrse.de//projects/rotary-table/&quot;&gt;Rotary Table&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;a class=&quot;right button tiny radius&quot; href=&quot;https://sgrse.de//projects/&quot;&gt;Project Overview&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>

			
				<category term="projects" />
			
			

			<published>2024-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		</entry>
	
</feed>